Register of the David Brombart papers, 1917-2009
Hoover Institution Archives
David Brombart papers
1917-2009
2009C36
Brombart, David, 1933-
23 manuscript boxes, 4 oversize boxes (12.8 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, reports, memoranda, conference materials, printed matter, photographs, and memorabilia, relating to the African-American Labor Center, the International Confederation of Free Trade Unions, and American Federation of Labor-Congress of Industrial Organizations participation in the international labor movement.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2009.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
1933 Born, St. Gilles-les-Bruxelles, Belgium
1954-1958 Youth secretary, Parti Socialiste Belge
1958-1964 Labor secretary, World Assembly of Youth, Paris and Brussels
1964-1979 Assistant to the executive director, AFL-CIO African-American Labor Center, New York
1975-1977 Member, United States delegation to the International Labour Organisation
1979-1983 AFL-CIO deputy director for international cooperation, London
1983-1986 Senior staff member, International Confederation of Free Trade Unions, Brussels
1986-1997 Deputy and acting executive director, AFL-CIO African-American Labor Center, Washington, D.C.
1997-2005 Senior fellow, Institute of International Studies, Washington, D.C.
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers of the Belgian-American labor official David Brombart primarily concern the involvement of the American Federation of Labor and Congress of Industrial Organizations (AFL-CIO) in the international labor movement, its opposition to the Communist-affiliated World Federation of Trade Unions (WFTU), and its cooperation with United States government agencies in fostering democratic trade unionism in Africa and elsewhere. Before joining the AFL-CIO, Brombart worked in the World Assembly of Youth (WAY), an international organization established in opposition to Communist front youth organizations, and funded in part by the United States Central Intelligence Agency. From its establishment in 1964 until his retirement in 1997, he was actively involved in the AFL-CIO's African-American Labor Center (AALC). He also represented the American labor movement in the International Labour Organisation (ILO) and in the International Confederation of Free Trade Unions (ICFTU).
The collection is arranged in twelve series. The first three, Personal Documents, Correspondence, and Speeches and Writings, consist of papers of David Brombart spanning the course of his career. The next five series document his work in specific capacities. They include the World Assembly of Youth File, International Labour Organization File, International Confederation of Free Trade Unions File, AFL-CIO File, and African-American Labor Center File. The AFL-CIO File covers activities of branches of that organization other than the African-American Labor Center. A Subject File is arranged topically and includes some material that might have been placed elsewhere (especially in the African-American Labor Center File), but that is narrowly focused on specific subjects. The Subject File also contains material on Islamic countries and other topics with which Brombart was concerned during later years as a fellow at the Institute of International Studies. The final three series, Audiovisual File, Memorabilia, and Oversize File consist of material that is distinctive because of physical format. The Audiovisual File includes a large number of photographs documenting activities of the organizations in which Brombart was involved.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
African-American Labor Center.; International Confederation of Free Trade Unions.; AFL-CIO.; Labor movement.; Labor movement--Africa.; Labor movement--United States.
Collection Contents
- Personal Documents, 1962-2009. (Folder 1)
  Personal identification cards, passports, certificates, invitations, clippings, and miscellany,
  - Passports and identification cards, 1970-1991 (Folder 1: 1)
  - Certificates, invitations, clippings, and miscellany, 1962-2009 (Folder 1: 2)
- Correspondence, 1939-2008. (Box 1--2)
  Correspondence, arranged alphabetically by correspondent
  - General (Box 1)
    - 1957-1979 (Folder 1: 3)
    - 1980-2008 (Folder 1: 4)
    - Undated (Folder 1: 5)
  - Attlee, Clement, 1956 (Folder 1: 6)
  - Beichman, Arnold, 1973-1995 (Folder 1: 7)
  - Blondel, Marc, 1997-1999 (Folder 1: 8)
  - Brown, Irving, 1964-1976 (Folder 1: 9)
  - Cabral, Amilcar, 1963 (Folder 1: 10)
  - Freeman, Anthony G. (Box 1)
    - 1996-2005 May (Folder 1: 11)
    - 2005 June-November (Folder 1: 12)
    - 2006 (Folder 1: 13)
  - Godson, Roy, 1984-2005 (Folder 1: 14)
  - Humphrey, Hubert H., 1968 (Folder 1: 15)
  - Kahn, Thomas, 1988-1990 (Folder 1: 16)
  - Kemble, Penn, 2001 (Folder 1: 17)
  - Kirkland, Lane, 1990 (Folder 1: 18)
  - Lovestone, Jay, 1967-1983 (Folder 1: 19)
  - Meany, George, 1973 (Folder 1: 20)
  - Muskie, Edmund S., 1971 (Folder 1: 21)
  - Perkins, Frances, 1939 (Folder 1: 22)
  - Rustin, Bayard, 1972 (Folder 1: 23)
  - Senser, Robert A., 2001-2002 (Folder 1: 24)
  - Simon, Paul, 1988-1989 (Folder 2: 1)
  - Tévoédjrè, Albert, 1973-1977 (Folder 2: 2)
  - Weiner, Herbert, 1981-1983 (Folder 2: 3)
- Speeches and Writings, 1966-1997. (Box 2--3)
  Speeches and writings by David Brombart, arranged chronologically
  - Speech re Africa, typescript notes, 1966 (Folder 2: 4)
  - Hypocrisy of Soviet 'Aid' to Developing Countries, AFL-CIO Free Trade Union News, 1970 December. (Folder 2: 5)
    Printed copy, and printed French and Italian translations
  - Brown Cites Principles of International Labor Solidarity, AALC Reporter, printed copy, 1971 July (Folder 2: 6)
  - Intercontinental Trade Unionism and U.S. Labor, typescript, 1973 February 23 (Folder 2: 7)
  - Report on the I.L.O., African-American Labor Center annual staff meeting presentation, typescript, 1977 April (Folder 2: 8)
  - Speech, International Confederation of Free Trade Unions forum, Nouakchott, Mauritania, Typescript (in French), 1978 March (Folder 2: 9)
  - Speech, Union Nationale des Travailleurs du Mali congress, Typescript (in French), 1978 July 17 (Folder 2: 10)
  - International Trade Union Gatherings, International Confederation of Free Trade Unions draft document, Typescript, 1987 (Folder 2: 11)
  - Arafat Meets the Social Democrats, Interco Press column, 1988 November. (Folder 2: 12)
    Printed Spanish translation only
  - Toward Reconciliation in South Africa, Interco Press column, 1989 May. (Folder 2: 13)
  - Speech, Union Marocaine du Travail congress, Casablanca, Morocco, Typescripts (in English and French), 1989 December (Folder 2: 14)
  - African Marxism and the Example of Benin, AFL-CIO Department of International Affairs Bulletin, Printed copy, 1990 (Folder 2: 15)
  - Introduction to AFL-CIO Program of Action in South Africa 1990 (pamphlet), Printed copy (Folder 2: 16)
  - No Peace Dividend for the International Free Trade Union Movement, Working materials, drafts, and processed copy, 1990 (Folder 2: 17)
  - Gorbatchev's Network of Interlocking Fronts Moving West, Conference on Soviet-Controlled Front Organizations in Crisis presentation, Rosslyn, Virginia, 1990 June 14. (Folder 2: 18)
    Draft, processed copy, and conference correspondence and agenda
  - England's Most Notorious Pro-Communist Labor Leader, Interco Press column, 1990 November. (Folder 2: 19)
    Printed Spanish and Portuguese translations only
  - Somalia's Torn History, Processed, 1991 (Folder 2: 20)
  - Zambia: Democracy and the Future of Africa, Interco Press column, Processed, 1991 (Folder 2: 21)
  - International Labor Condemns Iraq, Interco Press column, 1991 January. (Folder 2: 22)
    Printed Spanish, Hindi and Bengali translations only
  - The Angolan Spring, AFL-CIO Department of International Affairs Bulletin, Printed copy, 1991 February. (Folder 2: 23)
  - Liberia: Another African Tragedy, Interco Press column, 1991 July. Printed Spanish translation only (Folder 2: 24)
  - Speech, Hassan Fathy Institute conference, Bal Harbour, Florida, Processed, 1992 February 21. (Folder 2: 25)
  - Review of Joel Kotek, Students and the Cold War, Processed draft and correspondence, 1997 February 13. (Folder 2: 26)
  - Africa and Labour, Typescript (incomplete), undated. (Folder 2: 27)
  - African Trade Unionism in Question, Typescript, undated. (Folder 2: 28)
  - Speeches, Typescripts (in English and French), undated. (Folder 2: 29)
- World Assembly of Youth File, 1960-2009. (Box 2)
  Correspondence and printed matter by and about the World Assembly of Youth
  - Operational correspondence, 1960-1964. (Folder 2: 30)
    Mainly with Frank Ferrari
  - World Assembly of Youth issuances, 1962-1999. (Folder 2: 31)
    Includes New Trends and Development of Trade Unionism, 1963 (pamphlet); WAY Forum, 1969 (special 20th anniversary serial issue); and David Wirmark, The World Assembly of Youth (WAY) in the 50s and the 60s, 1999 (pamphlet)
  - Retrospective correspondence. Mainly with David Wirmark relating to a history-writing project on the World Assembly of Youth (Box 2)
    - 1967-1999 (Folder 2: 32)
    - 2000-2009 (Folder 2: 33)
  - Printed matter, 1964-2009. (Folder 3: 1)
    Bulletins, printed articles, and Internet printout, relating mainly to revelations of U.S. Central Intelligence Agency funding of the World Assembly of Youth. Includes David Maunders, "Controlling Youth for Democracy: The United States Youth Council and the World Assembly of Youth,
- International Labour Organization File, 1975-1980. (Box 3)
  Correspondence, personal documents, printed matter, and photographs (in scrapbooks) by and about the International Labour Organisation
  - General, 1975-1980. (Folder 3: 2)
    Letters, statement, and memoranda, press releases, and printed matter, relating to the withdrawal of the United States from the International Labour Organisation in 1977 and its return in 1980. Includes printed proceedings of several ILO sessions,
  - Scrapbooks, 1975-1977. (Folder 3: 3--4)
    Letters, personal documents, printed matter, and photographs, documenting David Brombart's service as a member of the American delegation to the ILO
- International Confederation of Free Trade Unions File, 1949-1999. (Box 3--4)
  Internal and public documents of the International Confederation of Free Trade Unions
  - General, 1980-1999. (Folder 3: 5)
    Memoranda, bulletins, correspondence, lists, and other internal documents emanating from the International Confederation of Free Trade Unions
  - May Day Manifesto, 1984 (Folder 3: 6)
    Draft manifesto by David Brombart for the International Confederation of Free Trade Unions, working materials, and printed copies (in English, French and Flemish)
  - International Trade Union News (publication of the International Confederation of Free Trade Unions), 1983-1984 (Folder 4: 1--2)
  - Miscellaneous International Confederation of Free Trade Unions publications, 1949-1988. (Folder 4: 3)
    Bulletins and pamphlets, including report of the preparatory founding conference, 1949; and constitution, 1983
- AFL-CIO File, 1959-2000. (Box 4--5)
  Internal and public documents of the American Federation of Labor and Congress of Industrial Organizations and of its various international institutes other than the African-American Labor Center
  - General, 1965-1996. (Folder 4: 4)
    Correspondence, memoranda, reports, minutes, planning documents, financial data, and other internal documents emanating from the AFL-CIO, and relating especially to its various international institutes and to their proposed consolidation
  - Convention (21st: 1995: New York). Printed matter from the convention (Folder 4: 5)
  - American Institute for Free Labor Development, 1987-1996. (Folder 4: 6)
    Correspondence, memoranda, and reports emanating from the American Institute for Free Labor Development
  - Asian-American Free Labor Institute, 1987-1996. (Folder 4: 7)
    Memoranda and reports emanating from the Asian-American Free Labor Institute
  - Committee on Defense, 1987 (Folder 4: 8)
    Report on the Strategic Defense Initiative to the AFL-CIO Executive Council by the AFL-CIO Committee on Defense
  - Department of International Affairs, 1990 (Folder 4: 9)
    "Across Frontiers: Spreading the Message of Free Trade Unionism: A Report on President Lane Kirkland's Visit to Poland and the USSR and an AFL-CIO Delegation to the Second Miners Congress in the USSR" (report by the AFL-CIO Department of International Affairs)
  - Free Trade Union Institute, 1992-1994. (Folder 4: 10)
    Report, memorandum, and brochure emanating from the Free Trade Union Institute
  - International Affairs Committee, 1994-1995. (Folder 5: 1)
    Consolidated reports of the various AFL-CIO international institutes to the AFL-CIO International Affairs Committee
  - Solidarity Center (American Center for International Labor Solidarity), 1999-2000. (Folder 5: 2)
    Report, brochure and personnel list emanating from the Solidarity Center
  - Miscellaneous AFL-CIO publications, 1959-1985. (Folder 5: 3)
    Pamphlets and serial issues, including Questions and Answers on American Labor and World Affairs, 1959 (pamphlet); and Wer ist der Imperialist?,
- African-American Labor Center File, 1964-1997. (Box 5--8)
  Internal and public documents of the AFL-CIO African American Labor Center, arranged chronologically
  - 1964-1966. (Folder 5: 4)
    Includes U.S. Department of State and U.S. Agency for International Development grant agreements; and Karl Butler, "Feasibility Study for the Establishment of a Pan-African Cooperative Training Center," 1966
  - 1967 (Folder 5: 5)
    Includes "Rapport préliminaire de la Conférence panafricaine coopérative" (Cotonou, Dahomey); and AALC Geneva, June 1967 (pamphlet)
  - 1968-1969. (Folder 5: 6)
    Includes U.S. Agency for International Development contract and operating procedures; "Second Exchange of Views" at the International Labour Organisation conference, 1968; and report of the Conférence Régionale Economique (Ouagadougou, Upper Volta), 1969
  - 1970-1972. (Folder 5: 7)
    Includes "Report on the Evaluation of Activities of the African-American Labor Center," 1972
  - 1973-1974. (Folder 6: 1)
    Includes U.S. Agency for International Development grant and audit; and George R. Martens, "Bibliography of African Trade Unionism," 1973
  - 1975-1977. (Folder 6: 2)
    Includes Africa's Trade Union Press, 1976 (report of Pan-African Colloquium on the Trade Union Press, Lomé, Togo,
  - 1978-1979. (Folder 6: 3)
    Includes proceedings of the African-American Trade Union Symposium on Employment and Trade, Abidjan, Côte d'Ivoire,
  - 1981-1983. (Folder 6: 4)
    Includes Georges Martens, "Le syndicalisme en Afrique occidentale d'expression française de 1945 à 1960," 1982; and "African Trade Unions: A List of African Trade Unions," 1983
  - 1985-1986. (Folder 6: 5)
    Includes AALC report of 1985 activities to its Board of Directors
  - 1987 (Folder 7: 1)
    Includes AALC report of 1987 activities to its Board of Directors
  - 1988 (Folder 7: 2)
    Includes audit; and grant budget submission to the U.S. Agency for International Development
  - 1989 (Folder 7: 3)
    Includes audit; and AALC report of 1989 activities to its Board of Directors
  - 1990 (Folder 7: 4)
    Includes audit; AALC report of 1990 activities to its Board of Directors; and project proposal for 1991-1995 submitted to the U.S. Agency for International Development
  - 1991-1992. (Folder 7: 5)
    Includes AALC report of 1992 activities to its Board of Directors
  - 1993-1994. (Folder 8: 1)
    Includes proceedings of Forum on Conditionality for the Defense of Worker Rights in Africa, San Francisco,
  - 1995 (Folder 8: 2)
    Includes directory of African trade union federations; program submission for 1996-2001 to the U.S. Agency for International Development; AALC report of 1995 activities to its Board of Directors; and proposed bylaw changes
  - 1996-1997. (Folder 8: 3)
    Includes descriptions of U.S. Agency of International Development program changes
  - Undated. (Folder 8: 4)
    Includes notes and summaries of unidentified international labor meetings with AALC participation in Geneva, Switzerland
- Subject File, 1917-2009. (Box 8--19)
  Correspondence, notes, memoranda, reports, speeches, lists, conference material, grant proposals, bulletins, printed articles, Internet printout, bibliographies, pamphlets, serial issues, clippings, and other printed matter, arranged alphabetically by topic. Includes internal and public documents of the African-American Labor Center relating to specific countries
  - Africa, 1951-1995. (Folder 8: 5)
    Material on Africa in general, and especially on labor in Africa. Includes Les peuples dépendants s'adressent aux Nations Unies: mémoire du Congrès des peuples, circa 1951 (pamphlet)
  - Algeria, 1997-2002. (Folder 8: 6)
    Relates mainly to the assassination of the Algerian labor leader Abdelhak Benhamouda in 1997
  - Ames, Aldrich (Soviet spy), 1994 (Folder 8: 7)
    Photocopy of U.S. Federal Bureau of Investigation affidavit in support of warrant for arrest of Ames and wife on espionage charges
  - Belgium, 1917-2006. (Folder 9: 1)
    Relates mainly to labor and socialist movements in Belgium. Includes Viscount Bryce, La dernière phase en Belgique, 1917; Le cinquantième anniversaire du P.O.B. [Parti Ouvrier Belge], 1885-1935: album-souvenir, 1935; Camille Huysmans, About Belgium,
  - Blondel, Marc (secretary-general, Force Ouvrière [France]), 1996 (Folder 9: 2)
    Includes speech by Blondel
  - Brown, Irving (director, AFL-CIO Department of International Affairs) (Box 9)
    - Personal papers of and writings by Brown, 1945-1980, including passport of Brown; memoranda and printed articles by Brown; "Alternatives to Wars of Attrition: The Role of Democratic Forces in a Political Solution," 1971 (typescript by Brown); "Labor and the Developing World," 1971 (typescript by Brown); and letters to Brown (Folder 9: 3)
    - Tributes to Brown and printed matter about him, 1946-1988. (Folder 9: 4)
      Includes French Communist broadside denouncing him
    - Obituaries of Brown and condolence letters upon his death, 1989 (Folder 9: 5)
  - Burma, 1996 (Folder 9: 6)
  - Canada, 1989 (Folder 9: 7)
  - Central America, 1985-1986. (Folder 9: 8)
    Includes James McCargar, "El Salvador and Nicaragua: The AFL-CIO Views on the Controversy," 1985 (AFL-CIO Department of International Affairs document); and Tom Barry and Deb Preusch, "AIFLD in Central America: Agents as Organizers," 1986
  - China, 1989 (Folder 9: 9)
  - Committee for International Support of Trade Union Rights, 1988-1990 (Folder 9: 10)
  - Communism. Relates to international communism in general and especially to international Communist front organizations (Box 10)
    - General, 1983-1999 (Folder 10: 1)
    - Report on Communist-Controlled Organisations, 1986-1992; "The Communist Propaganda Network and Perestroika," 1990; W. Spaulding, "World Communism in 1992," 1992; and W. Spaulding, "World Communism: Current Status and Future Prospects," 1993 (Folder 10: 2)
  - Communism-United States (Box 10)
    - General, 1987-2002 (Folder 10: 3)
    - Dilling, Elizabeth, The Red Network, 1934 (book) (Folder 10: 4)
  - Dahomey, circa 1990. (Folder 10: 5)
    Ambroise Agboton Padonou, J'ai survécu (pamphlet)
  - Egypt, 1993-2000. (Folder 10: 6)
    Relates mainly to AALC and Solidarity Center programs in Egypt
  - Europe, 1993-2002. (Folder 10: 7)
    Includes Sara-Nathalie Brombart, "Uneasy Partners in Foreign Policy-Making: European Political Cooperation and the European Community," 1993; and Rebecca Gumbrell-McCormick, "The Role of Nordic Trade Unions in the International Labour Movement," 2002
  - France, 1940-2003. (Folder 10: 8)
    Relates mainly to Force Ouvrière and other labor movements, and to Trotskyism, in France. Includes Pierre Galoni, "Conférence Franco-américaine des 14 et 15 janvier 1972," 1972; Diana Pinto, "Hamon and Rotman: La Deuxième Gauche," 1983; and Jean-Marie Pernot, "Les relations internationales et les débuts de la CGT-FO," 2003
  - Freeman, Anthony G. (U.S. Department of State labor affairs officer and International Labour Organisation official), 2007 (Folder 11: 1)
    Obituary and related material
  - Funk, Jerry (AFL-CIO and U.S. government official), 2002-2004 (Folder 11: 2)
  - Germany, 1979-1984. Includes German-American Trade Union Solidarity in the Struggle against Fascism, 1933-1945: How the American Trade Unions Helped their Persecuted German Colleagues, 1984 (pamphlet) (Folder 11: 3)
  - Godson, Roy (president, Institute for International Studies), 1975-1995. Mainly printed writings by Godson. Includes his "American Labor's Continuing Involvement in World Affairs," 1975; "The AFL Foreign Policy Making Process from the End of World War II to the Merger," 1975; The Kremlin and Labor: A Study in National Security Policy, 1977; and Soviet Active Measures, People-to-People Contacts, and the Helsinki Process, 1986 (Folder 11: 4)
  - Institute for Policy Studies, 1981 (Folder 11: 5)
  - Intelligence, 1967-2009. (Folder 11: 6)
    Relates to intelligence operations and espionage in general. Includes several issues of Political Warfare, 1990-1992; Of Moles and Molehunters: A Review of Counterintelligence Literature,
  - International Centre for Trade Union Rights, 1990-2005 (Folder 11: 7)
  - International Conference on Disarmament, Development and Conversion (1990: Copenhagen). Conference materials (Folder 11: 8)
  - International Endowment for Democracy, 2006 (Folder 11: 9)
  - International Federation of Trade Unions, 1964 (Folder 11: 10)
    Walther Schevenels, Quarante-cinq années: Fédération Syndicale Internationale,
  - International Workers' Conference in Solidarity with the Workers and People of the State of Kuwait (1990: Cairo). Conference material, relating to the Iraqi invasion of Kuwait, correspondence, and press coverage (Folder 11: 11)
  - Iraq, 1997-2006. (Folder 11: 12)
    Includes Felix Zorba and Roberto Sarti, "Uprisings and Betrayals: A Brief History of the Left in Iraq," 2003 (Internet article)
  - Islamic countries (Box 12)
    - General, 1993-2006 (Folder 12: 1)
    - Hassan Fathy Institute. Relates to efforts of the Hassan Fathy Institute, in conjunction with the International Construction Institute, to promote democratic construction trade unions in Islamic countries (Box 12)
      - Grant proposals to the AFL-CIO Solidarity Center, the U.S. Agency for International Development and the National Endowment for Democracy; concept papers; and correspondence with John T. Joyce, 2002-2006 (Folder 12: 2--3)
      - Printed reports, 1988-2000 (Folder 12: 4)